Register of the Alfred Max Loewenthal papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Alfred Max Loewenthal papers
1886-1980
80189
Hoover Institution Archives
59 manuscript boxes, 5 oversize boxes, 2 motion picture film reels (25.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes, serial issues, other printed matter, and motion picture film relating to electrical workers' unions in the United States, to teachers' unions in the United States and abroad, and to socialism, communism, and Trotskyism in the United States and especially in the labor movement.
Loewenthal, Alfred Max, 1916-1980
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1916 Born, Newark, New Jersey
1941 Charter member, Local 447, United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers Union, Nutley, New Jersey
1948-1956 Business agent, Local 447, United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers Union (subsequently International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers)
1955-1965 Director, Union Leadership Academy, Rutgers University
1956-1961 Education director, District 4, International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers
1961-1965 Assistant to the president, District 4 (subsequently District 3), International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers
1963 Democratic Party candidate for mayor of Verona, New Jersey
1964 Candidate for Democratic Party nomination for Congress, 12th Congressional District of New Jersey
1965-1967 Assistant to the president, International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers
1967-1970 Public relations director, American Federation of Teachers
1970-1979 Assistant to the president, American Federation of Teachers
1980 Died, Baltimore, Maryland
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Alfred Max Loewenthal, an official of electrical workers' and teachers' unions, are concerned with the intersection of labor and communism, and with the intersection of labor and education. They deal with the issue of Communist Party influence in American unions and also with AFL-CIO efforts to counteract communist influence in unions abroad. They also deal with educational activities of unions and with the unionization of educational workers.
Loewenthal joined the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers Union (UE) in 1941 as a rank-and-file member on the shop floor. The UE was a major union within the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) and one in which the Communist Party gained substantial influence. Loewenthal, however, was aligned within his Local 447 with an anti-Communist faction. With the onset of the Cold War, the CIO adopted a policy of requiring its constituent unions to purge themselves of pro-Communist officials. When the UE refused to comply, it was expelled in 1949, and the CIO proceeded to charter a rival union, the International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers (IUE). Loewenthal, by then business agent of Local 447, was instrumental in leading his local out of the UE and into the new IUE. He rose within the IUE to become assistant to President Milton Weihrauch of District 4 (subsequently redesignated District 3), which represented more than 100,000 electrical workers in New York and New Jersey. Factionalism continued, albeit in new form, within the IUE. The 1964 reelection of James B. Carey, president of the IUE since its inception, was found by the National Labor Relations Board to have been tainted by fraud, and the results were overturned. Paul Jennings, installed as IUE president despite lesser irregularities in his own campaign, appointed Loewenthal as his assistant. A rift arose between Jennings and Weihrauch, hitherto allies, which came to a head when misuse of District 3 union funds was uncovered. Weihrauch was ousted, and Loewenthal, though not accused of wrongdoing by anyone, was fired by Jennings. The UE, which had maintained its existence as an independent union outside the AFL-CIO, viewed the disarray within the IUE with considerable glee. This ended Loewenthal's electrical union career, which is documented in the ELECTRICAL WORKERS' UNIONS FILE.
While still a Local 447 official, Loewenthal began to specialize in union educational activities. He was founder and director in 1955 of the Union Leadership Academy, sponsored by the IUE in conjunction with the Rutgers University Institute of Management and Labor Relations and the Cornell University School of Industrial and Labor Relations to provide leadership training for union members. He continued as educational director of District 4 and was charged with community relations, human rights, and international contact functions, as well as educational affairs, for District 4 and later for the entire IUE. His labor educational activities are documented in the LABOR EDUCATION FILE, which also covers the one-year appointment he received after leaving the IUE as professor of labor history at Rutgers University, despite his lack of the customary academic credentials.
Loewenthal became an official of the American Federation of Teachers (AFT) in 1967, initially as public relations director and subsequently as assistant to successive AFT Presidents David Selden and Albert Shanker. In addition to concerns with the relationship between collective bargaining and professionalism as affecting teachers and other educational workers, Loewenthal continued to specialize in human rights and international affairs issues for the AFT. In its international aspects, he was in close touch with the AFL-CIO Department of International Affairs and related bodies, such as the African-American Labor Center, the Asian-American Free Labor Institute, and the American Institute for Free Labor Development. The AMERICAN FEDERATION OF TEACHERS FILE documents his general work for the union. Contacts with teachers' unions in other countries are covered in the INTERNATIONAL TEACHERS' UNIONS FILE.
Loewenthal's early political history is not explicitly documented in the collection. Leaflets of opposing factions in the IUE labeled him a Trotskyist. The LEFT-WING PUBLICATIONS file does include a large volume of Trotskyist literature from the 1930s and 1940s, including internal bulletins, suggesting that he may indeed have been a member or sympathizer of the Socialist Workers Party during his youth. If so, he put that period behind him. He was heavily involved in Democratic Party politics by the early 1960s. Loewenthal was the Democratic candidate for mayor of Verona, New Jersey, in 1963, and in 1964 unsuccessfully sought the Democratic nomination for Congress from the 12th Congressional District of New Jersey. These campaigns are documented in the ELECTION CAMPAIGN FILE. Loewenthal's mature politics were anti-communist and liberal. He was a strong supporter of Israel and of the American Jewish community, a strong supporter of the black civil rights movement, and an opponent of nuclear weapons testing. In the 1970s he was close to Social Democrats, U.S.A.
The SPEECHES AND WRITINGS file includes Loewenthal's own writings from all periods of his life. The SUBJECT FILE consists of collected material, mainly printed matter, arranged topically. The OVERSIZE FILE notably contains oversize publications of the IUE and of Trotskyist organizations. The small AUDIOVISUAL FILE is associated with Loewenthal's IUE period.
The Hoover Institution acquired the collection from Eleanor Loewenthal in 1980 following her husband's death.
Portions of the collection have suffered from water damage.
The abbreviations AFT, IUE and UE are used throughout the register.
American Federation of Teachers.; Fourth International.; International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers.; Communism--United States.; Electric industry workers--United States.; Labor unions--United States.; Socialism--United States.; Teachers' unions--United States.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1953-1980 (Boxes 1-2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Speeches and writings by Alfred Loewenthal, arranged chronologically.
  - Orientation address, IUE District 4 Leadership Institute, Newark, New Jersey, 1953 April 11 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Typescript
  - "IUE Instructor Program Starts Second Year," AFL-CIO Education News and Views, 1957 April (Box-folder 1: 2)
    Printed copy
  - "Cause of Inflation," letter to the editor, Newark Evening News, 1957 October 13 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - "Public Libraries and the Experience of the ULA," Library Service to Labor Newsletter, 1958 Spring (Box-folder 1: 4)
    Mimeograph
  - "New Frontiers Clubs: A People's Lobby,", 1961 February 8 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - "Sees Self-Interest Campaign," letter to the editor, Verona Cedar-Grove Times, 1961 May 4 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Speech, Unemployed Out-of-School Youth Conference, Newark, New Jersey, 1961 November 30 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - "Autumn Fallout" (poem re nuclear testing), 1961 December 12 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - "Human Rights vs. Property Rights," letter to the editor, Verona Cedar-Grove Times, 1962 April 12 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Letter to the editor, Verona Cedar-Grove Times, re local elections, 1962 November 9 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - "Travel Time," letter to the editor, 1962 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Acceptance speech as Democratic Party nominee for mayor of Verona, New Jersey, 1963 February 28 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - "Jewish Labor: Then and Now," speech, Jewish Labor Committee National Trade Union Conference on Civil Rights, Unity House, Pennsylvania, 1963 September 16 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    Typescript, and printed copy of version published as "The Future of Jewish Labor," Workmen's Circle Call, 1964 January.
  - "Timely Tour," letter to the editor, Newark Evening News, 1963 September 27 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - "Voting for Jobs," letter to the editor, Newark Evening News, 1963 December 29 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Speech re labor and desegregation, Temple Sholom, River Edge, New Jersey, 1964 January 3 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    Holograph (incomplete)
  - Announcement of candidacy for Democratic Party nomination for Congress, 12th Congressional District of New Jersey, 1964 January 14 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - "Conversion as a Community Concern" (re defense industry conversion), 1964 March 31 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - "On 'Unions and Jews,'" letter to the editor, Jewish Advocate, 1964 April 16 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Speech, Histadrut Conference, Unity House, Pennsylvania, 1964 May (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Speech, Histadrut Trade Union Leadership Seminar, Herzlia, Israel, 1964 July 28 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Speech, B'nai B'rith Brotherhood Awards Celebration, 1964 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Letter to the editor, Verona-Cedar Grove Times, re student protesters, 1965 February 1 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Letter to the editor, Verona-Cedar Grove Times, re housing restrictions, 1965 March 22 (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - "Labor and the Great Society," speech, Labor Zionist Eastern Seaboard Seminar, Atlantic City, New Jersey, 1965 March 27 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - "The Positive Outcome of the IUE Mission to the CVT," report re IUE contribution to Confédération Vietnamienne du Travail refugee resettlement project in South Vietnam, 1966 July 18 (Box-folder 1: 26)
    Typescript and background materials
  - "Global Effects of Parleys with U.S. Electrical 'Giants,'" AFL-CIO Free Trade Union News, 1966 September (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - Unused speech re union corruption investigations prepared for IUE District 3 Executive Board meeting, 1967 June 13 (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Appeal to IUE International Executive Board for reinstatement, 1967 June 28 (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - Letter to the editor, Wall Street Journal, re illegal strikes, 1968 February 8 (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - Letter to the editor, Newark Evening News, re teachers' strike, 1968 February 19 (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - "Teacher Militancy: A New Element in Labor's Image," speech, Conference on Labor's Public Image, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana, 1968 December 13-14 (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - "Implications of the General Electric Strike and Coordinated Bargaining,", 1969 (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - Contribution to New America Symposium on Labor and the Intellectuals, 1971 (Box-folder 1: 34)
    Typescript and mimeograph
  - Bargaining for Academic Democracy (with Robert Nielsen; pamphlet), 1976 March (Box-folder 1: 35)
  - Report on White House Conference on Arts Education, 1976 September 13 (Box-folder 1: 36)
  - "Spirit of Israel: Solidarity, Democracy," American Teacher, 1976 November (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - "IFFTU/AFT Asian Survey Mission,", 1977 March (Box-folder 1: 38)
  - "Unions in Academia: A Bargaining Frontier" (with Robert Nielsen), AFL-CIO American Federationist, 1977 April (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - Speech re labor history, AFT conference, Houston, Texas, 1977 June (Box-folder 1: 40)
  - Review of Roy Godson, American Labor and European Politics: The AFL as a Transitional Force, 1977 November 10 (Box-folder 1: 41)
  - "The American Federation of Teachers and Trade Unionism," speech outline, 1977 (Box-folder 1: 42)
  - Introduction to Intellectuals, Academics and the Labor Movement (pamphlet), 1977 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Unionism and Professionalism: Siblings? (with Robert Nielsen; pamphlet), 1977 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - "History Is on the Side of Public Schools," American Teacher, 1978 April (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - "The Palestinians," speech, Joint Symposium on Labor, Democracy and Development in the Middle East, 1978 May 31 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - "On Unionism's Frontiers" (with Robert Nielsen), Universitas, 1978 September (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - "The IFFTU/AFT Work-Study Mission to African Teachers Organizations and Unions,", 1978 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - "International Affairs and Teacher Union Education,", 1978 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Report on Taiwan Teachers' Organizations (with Mary-Ellen Riordan), 1979 January 10 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Report on Second Leadership Seminar, Trinidad and Tobago Teachers Union and American Federation of Teachers, 1979 January (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Report on visit to Belize National Teachers' Union 9th Annual Convention, 1979 April 25 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Report on National Alliance of Teachers and Office Workers (Philippines), 1979 June 4 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - "Perspectives for Work in International Affairs,", 1979 August 3 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - "The Meaning of Yeshiva: A Union Now, More than Ever,", 1980 April (Box-folder 2: 13)
- ELECTRICAL WORKERS' UNIONS FILE, 1935-1979 (Boxes 2-16)
  Papers relating to the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers Union and to the International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers.
  - General, 1942-1968
    Memoranda, reports, statements, resolutions, bulletins, announcements, notices, circulars, programs, press releases, notes, curricula vitae, rosters, convention excerpts, legal records, and financial records.
    - 1942-1945 (Box-folder 2: 14)
      Includes transcripts of interrogatories of union members re unauthorized walkout by members of Local 447.
    - 1946-1947 (Box-folder 2: 15)
      Includes resolution re communist issue.
    - 1948 (Box-folder 2: 16)
    - 1949 (Box-folder 2: 17)
      Includes Congress of Industrial Organizations resolution on expulsion of UE.
    - 1950-1952 (Box-folder 3: 1)
      Includes Loewenthal's non-communist affidavit as a union officer and report on oppositionists within District 4.
    - 1953-1954 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - 1955 (Box-folder 3: 3)
      Includes notes on history of Local 447.
    - 1956 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - 1957-1959 (Box-folder 3: 5)
      Includes speech by Al Hartnett.
    - 1960-1961 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - 1962 (Box-folder 4: 2)
      Includes draft statement on Cuban Missile Crisis.
    - 1963 (Box-folder 4: 3)
      Includes IUE Constitution.
    - 1964 (Box-folder 4: 4-5)
      Includes IUE program by James B. Carey, audit reports, and reports and circulated correspondence re intra-union lawsuit and dispute between IUE international office and District 3.
    - 1965 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 4: 7-8)
      Includes reports and other material re IUE contributions to Vietnamese refugee resettlement, prospective purchase of Philip Murray Building, severance payments for James B. Carey, and investigation of District 3 finances.
    - 1967 (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
      Includes memoranda, reports, circulated correspondence, and legal records re investigation of District 3 finances, ouster of Milton Weihrauch as president of District 3, lawsuit by Weihrauch against the IUE, and dismissal of Loewenthal by President Paul Jennings.
    - 1968 (Box-folder 5: 3)
      Subpoena for Loewenthal to testify in U.S. District Court.
  - Correspondence, 1946-1977
    - General, 1946-1977
      - 1946-1956 (Box-folder 5: 4)
      - 1957-1963 (Box-folder 5: 5)
      - 1964-1977 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - AFL-CIO (national office; George Meany, Jay Lovestone), 1957-1968 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - Abramson and Lewis (law firm), 1962-1966 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    - Americans for Democratic Action, 1963 (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, 1963 (Box-folder 5: 10)
    - Arnold, Dan, 1967 (Box-folder 5: 11)
    - Bywater, William, 1968 (Box-folder 5: 12)
    - Carey, James B., 1949-1965 (Box-folder 5: 13)
    - Case, Clifford P., 1966 (Box-folder 5: 14)
    - Confédération Vietnamienne du Travail, 1967 (Box-folder 5: 15)
    - Congress of Industrial Organizations (national and regional offices), 1950-1952 (Box-folder 5: 16)
    - Ditchley Foundation, 1966 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Douglas, Paul H., 1966 (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - Drohan, William D., 1951-1969 (Box-folder 6: 3)
    - Federal Telephone and Radio Company (International Telephone and Telegraph Corporation), 1955-1968 (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - Hanley, James M., 1966 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - Helstoski, Henry, 1965 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - Histadrut (General Federation of Labor of Israel, American Trade Union Council of the National Committee for Labor Israel), 1962-1965 (Box-folder 6: 7)
    - Hughes, Richard J., 1965 (Box-folder 6: 8)
    - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1960 (Box-folder 6: 9)
    - International Confederation of Free Trade Unions (Irving Brown), 1965 (Box-folder 6: 10)
    - International Labour Office, 1965 (Box-folder 6: 11)
    - International Metalworkers' Federation, 1965 (Box-folder 6: 12)
    - Islamic Center (Washington, D.C.), 1965-1966 (Box-folder 6: 13)
    - Israel. Embassy (U.S.), 1962-1965 (Box-folder 6: 14)
    - Jacobson, Joel R., 1951-1967 (Box-folder 6: 15)
    - Jennings, Paul, 1965-1970 (Box-folder 6: 16)
    - Jewish Labor Committee (Emanuel Muravchik, Charles S. Zimmerman), 1957-1965 (Box-folder 6: 17)
    - Kapelsohn, Lerner, Leuchter and Reitman (law firm), 1953-1973 (Box-folder 6: 18)
    - Kennedy, Edward M., 1967 (Box-folder 6: 19)
    - Kennedy, John F. and Jacqueline, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 6: 20)
    - Labor Zionist Organization of America, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 6: 21)
    - Leopaldi, Jerry, 1953-1972 (Box-folder 6: 22)
    - Liberal Party of New York State (Charles S. Zimmerman), 1963 (Box-folder 6: 23)
    - Minish, Joseph G., 1955-1966 (Box-folder 6: 24)
    - Mississippi Free Press, 1963 (Box-folder 6: 25)
    - Mollohan, Robert H., 1955 (Box-folder 6: 26)
    - Morse, Wayne, 1963 (Box-folder 6: 27)
    - National Labor Service (Harry Fleischman), 1956 (Box-folder 6: 28)
    - New Jersey. Department of Labor and Industry, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 6: 29)
    - New Jersey. State Board of Mediation, 1956 (Box-folder 6: 30)
    - Promoting Enduring Peace, Inc. (Jerome Davis), 1960-1961 (Box-folder 6: 31)
    - Puzo, Joseph, 1955-1959 (Box-folder 6: 32)
    - Riesel, Victor, 1965 (Box-folder 6: 33)
    - Rodino, Peter W., Jr., 1952 (Box-folder 6: 34)
    - Ryan, William F., 1964 (Box-folder 6: 35)
    - SANE (National Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy), 1964 (Box-folder 6: 36)
    - Southern Christian Leadership Conference (Martin Luther King, Jr.), 1963 (Box-folder 6: 37)
    - Stevenson, Adlai E., 1962 (Box-folder 6: 38)
    - Suarez, Jack R., 1965-1967 (Box-folder 6: 39)
    - United Auto Workers Union (Emil Mazey), 1958-1966 (Box-folder 6: 40)
    - United States. Aid Mission to Vietnam (Emil G. Lindahl), 1966-1967 (Box-folder 6: 41)
    - United States. Department of Justice, 1956 (Box-folder 6: 42)
    - United States. Department of Labor (W. Willard Wirtz), 1960-1966 (Box-folder 6: 43)
    - United States. Information Agency, 1963 (Box-folder 6: 44)
    - Urban League, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 6: 45)
    - Weihrauch, Milton, 1949-1967 (Box-folder 6: 46)
  - Minutes, 1946-1966
    - 1946-1949 (Box-folder 7: 1)
      Local 447 minute book for 1946-1949 and other loose Local 447 minutes.
    - 1952-1966 (Box-folder 7: 2)
      Mainly District 4/District 3 Executive Board minutes. Includes some IUE international minutes, Local 447 minutes, and other miscellaneous minutes.
  - Factional literature, 1943-1964
    - 1943-1948 (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - 1949 (Box-folder 7: 4)
      Includes "The Case of UE Local 447."
    - 1951-1957 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - 1961-1962 (Box-folder 7: 6)
      Includes anti-Weihrauch leaflets labeling Loewenthal a Trotskyist.
    - 1964 (Box-folder 8: 1)
      Relates mainly to contested election between James B. Carey and Paul Jennings. Includes anti-Jennings leaflets labeling Loewenthal a Trotskyist.
  - Grievance proceedings, 1945-1956
    Correspondence, memoranda, and proceeding transcripts relating to Local 447 individual grievance cases.
    - 1945-1953 (Box-folder 8: 2)
    - 1954 (Box-folder 8: 3)
    - 1955 (Box-folder 8: 4)
    - 1956 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - Pension and benefit agreements for employees of Federal Radio and Telephone Company and International Telephone and Telegraph Corporation, 1935-1952 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - Schedules, 1955-1967 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Security clearance issues, 1955-1956 (Box-folder 9: 2)
    Correspondence and legal records re work requiring national security classification clearances, and re Communist Party membership employment issues.
  - Tactical Air Navigation equipment production, 1956 (Box-folder 9: 3)
    Correspondence with United States government officials re electrical production work on these Air Force systems.
  - Wage and contract negotiations, 1954-1956
    Correspondence, proposals, agreements, notes, statistics, background materials, and press coverage re IUE collective bargaining with Federal Radio and Telephone Company and International Telephone and Telegraph Corporation.
    - 1954 (Box-folder 9: 4)
    - 1955 (Box-folder 9: 5)
    - 1956 (Box-folder 9: 6)
    - 1956 (cont'd.) (Box-folder 10: 1-2)
  - UE publications, 1937-1968
    - 1937-1948 (Box-folder 10: 3)
      Issues of, and articles from, UE newspaper People's Press and from Local 447 newspapers and newsletters, and Local 447 Constitution and By-Laws.
    - 1950 (Box-folder 10: 4)
      UE 15th convention proceedings, New York, New York.
    - 1955-1968 (Box-folder 11: 1)